Finding Aid for Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan) Records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan) Records 1922-1979 1967-1972
Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan)
9675 Aa 2
Youth camp founded in 1921 by member of University of Michigan Student Christian Association to provide outdoor experience for underprivileged youths, management assumed by University of Michigan Institute for Human Adjustment in 1944 and later by the School of Education when emphasis changed to serving physically handicapped children. Records document management of the camp including reports on camp activities and research conducted at the camp.
2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group (Accession No. 804 ) was received through the School of Education in 1995.
The collection is open for research.
The University of Michigan Fresh Air Camp was started in 1921 by Lewis Reimann and Thomas Evans, the former of whom served as the camp's first director. The camp began as a volunteer driven organization of students involved with the Student Christian Association, with the goal of providing outdoor experience to underprivileged, mostly urban youth. For the first three years, the camp was held in different locations, but in 1924, through a gift of Virginia Ives, it acquired a permanent site on Patterson Lake near Pinckney, Michigan.
The camp served dual purposes of providing an atmosphere for difficult youth to learn and grow and a place for university students, who would serve as counselors, to practice skills in education, psychology, social work, and related fields. In 1937, the university began offering Summer Session graduate courses through the camp, and in 1944 the camp was accepted by the Board of Regents. Upon entering into university jurisdiction, the camp was administratively housed within the Institute for Human Adjustment and remained there into the 1960s when it moved into the School of Education.
Within the School of Education, the camp began to focus more on mentally handicapped children. Under the direction of Matthew Trippe and Raymond Elliot, both faculty members of the School of Education, the Fresh Air Camp secured a grant through the Federal Education Professions Development Act, which they used to further study the education of "exceptional children." The camp often served as the subject for advanced research studies in adolescent education and psychology and continued to provide the opportunity for both graduate and undergraduate students to work with "at risk" children and gain experience within their chosen field. Although the Fresh Air Camp changed administrative and educational focus through its years of operation under the School of Education, the camp remained committed to its goal of providing a safe, fun, and friendly environment in which its campers could learn and grow.
The records of the University of Michigan Fresh Air Camp are comprised of materials documenting the functions, operations, policies, and events of the camp. Records range from the early 1920s to the late 1970s, but are strongest in the periods from approximately 1937-1950 and especially 1967-1972. Researchers will take particular interest in the annual reports and other materials found in the Reports series, which document the activities of the camp and include pertinent historical information. Records documenting a grant received by the school in the late 1960s through the Federal Education Profession Development Act also provide an excellent overview of the camp's philosophy at that time.
The records of the Fresh Air Camp are arranged in the following four series:
Administrative File, 1922-1977 (1.1 linear ft.)
Activities, 1965-1971 (0.3 linear ft.)
Reports, 1927-1971 (0.3 linear ft.)
Visual Materials, 1969-ca. 1970s (0.3 linear ft.)
Subjects:
Reimann, Lewis Charles.; Evans, Thomas.; Trippe, Matthew J.; Elliot, Raymond.; Fresh Air Camp (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. School of Education.; University of Michigan. Institute for Human Adjustment.; Camps for mentally handicapped children--Michigan.; Camps--Michigan.; School camps--Michigan.; Mentally handicapped children--Education--Michigan.; Outdoor education--Michigan.
- Administrative File 1922-1977, 1.1 linear feet
  The Administrative File contains an incomplete run of materials from throughout the history of the camp. It includes a small amount of correspondence, scattered meeting minutes of the executive committee, grant applications and reports, financial records and staff and student information. The financial records include information on the land purchase and a sketch showing the location of the land. Staff manuals provide documentation of camp policy, activities, participation, and routine administrative functions such as counselor applications. Two ledgers are included within this series, the first of which lists students and counselors from 1922 to 1932. Information includes names, age, church, and sponsoring organization. The second ledger is a record of medical treatment covering the 1979 season.
  - Consultant Evaluations 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (scattered)
  - Education Professions Development Act Grant
    - Annual Reports 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Director's Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Grant Proposal 1971 (Box 1)
    - Research Studies 1972 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee 1929-1960 (Box 1)
    scattered
  - Financial Materials
    - Camp Inventory 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - Commodity Foods, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Imprest Cash Fund 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Land Purchase 1924 (Box 1)
    - Milk Program 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - History, 1937, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Physical Plant, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Staff File
    - Academic Materials 1971 (Box 1)
    - Camper Report Guidelines 1971 (Box 1)
    - Counselor Applications 1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Personnel Lists 1924-1951, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Senior Staff Meeting Notes 1970 (Box 1)
  - Staff Manuals
    - 1935 (Box 1)
    - 1968-1977, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Student Ledgers
    - Camp Ledger 1922-1932 (Box 2)
    - Medical Record 1979 (Box 2)
- Activities 1965-1971, 0.3 linear feet
  The Activities series gives examples of the types of activities offered at the camp. The folders contain reports, schedules, and inventories from each activity area of the camp. These records are predominantly from the late 1960s and early 1970s and replicate some of the information found in the staff manuals.
  - General 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Camp Craft 1967 (Box 2)
  - Education Program 1967 (Box 2)
  - Expressive Arts, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Filmstrips, 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - Hobby Shop, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Movies, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Nature, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Newspapers, 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1967 (Box 2)
  - Science, undated (Box 2)
  - Stories, undated (Box 2)
  - Waterfront, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
- Reports 1927-1971, 0.3 linear feet
  The Reports series includes an incomplete run of annual reports, which range from detailed printed items to loosely bound type-written pages. They usually include financial information and other statistics for the camping season they cover, and a few of the early reports include photographs. A 1967 report of the camp's educational program offers an in-depth analysis on the subject.
  - Annual Reports 1927-1971, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Education Program 1967 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials, circa 1969-1970s, 0.3 linear feet
  Over two hundred, mostly black and white photographs, negatives and slides shot primarily during the 1970s, comprise the Visual Materials series. The images are separated into Grounds, Groups (pictures of campers and staff normally engaged in activities) and Individuals (pictures of one or two campers usually posing for the camera). Also housed here is a 1969 program comprised of slides and a 5 inch reel-to-reel audio tape (3 3/4 ips) documenting activities at Camp Tamarack. The program was created through the School of Education and documents related activities at this camp for university junior high school students located near Ortonville, Michigan.
  - Photographs
    - Grounds (Box 2)
    - Groups, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Individuals, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Negatives, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Camp Tamarack Slide and Tape Program, 1969, 5 inch; 3 3/4 ips; reel-to-reel-tape (Box 2)
Related Material
A film Fresh Air Camp is located in the University of Michigan Media Resources Center record group.